<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2342 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2342.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3501 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3501.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4549 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4549.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5162 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5162.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5246 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5255 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5255.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-imap-suspend-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title>IMAP SUSPEND Extension</title>

    <author fullname="Michael M. Slusarz" initials="M.M." surname="Slusarz">
      <organization>Horde LLC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city>Denver</city>
          <region>Colorado</region>
          <code></code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>slusarz@horde.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2012"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>IETF</workgroup>

    <keyword>IMAP</keyword>
    <keyword>SUSPEND</keyword>
    <keyword>RESUME</keyword>
    <keyword>disconnected</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines the SUSPEND extension for the IMAP protocol.
      It provides a method for a client to save the current configuration
      state of an IMAP session and then quickly restore this configuration
      in a subsequent session.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>[TODO: Reorganize this section. Disconnected talk should probably
      go lower in section, after talk about activating extensions.]</t>

      <t>The original IMAP4rev1 <xref target="RFC3501"/>
      protocol specification was primarily designed to be used by clients
      that remain connected to the IMAP server for extended periods of
      time. Since that time, "disconnected" IMAP clients
      <xref target="RFC4549"/> have become increasingly popular and
      numerous, due to the rise in, for example, portable devices that
      do not maintain persistent connections to the remove server, or for
      which keeping an active connection is expensive (in terms of
      computing and/or power).</t>

      <t>In response to the rise of these disconnected clients, various
      IMAP extensions have been developed to assist in accessing the
      remote account. [TODO: Links to LEMONADE profile? UIDPLUS?] Some
      of these extensions, such as <xref target="RFC5162">QRESYNC</xref>,
      require explicit action by the client in order to activate their
      features.</t>

      <t>Other advanced IMAP features, such as the
      <xref target="RFC5255">LANGUAGE command</xref>, also require explicit
      configuration by the client and is forgotten when the client logs out
      of the server [TODO: mention NOTIFY?].</t>

      <t>Finally, there is additional overhead when connecting to an
      IMAP server (e.g. entering authenticated state) because the client
      needs to do things like determine the capabilities of the remote
      server (<xref target="RFC3501">CAPABILITY command</xref>) and, if
      available, to obtain the namespace layout for the mailboxes
      (<xref target="RFC2342">NAMESPACE command</xref>).</t>

      <t>Therefore, a disconnected client still faces the (potentially
      substantial) overhead of needing to perform various initialization
      initialization tasks before the client can begin to do "useful"
      work from the perspective of the end user (e.g. listing mailboxes
      accessing messages). For clients that are unable to maintain a
      persistent connection the server, many of the gains provided by
      the advanced IMAP extensions are offset by the overhead to enable
      and confgure them on every access.</t>

      <t>The SUSPEND extension provides a mechanism for a client to save
      the configuration state of an existing session and then quickly
      re-establish this configuration in subsequent server connections.</t>

      <t>An IMAP server that supports SUSPEND advertises this by including
      the word SUSPEND in its capability list.</t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>

        <t>In examples, lines beginning with "S:" are sent by the IMAP server,
        and lines beginning with "C:" are sent by the client.  Line breaks
        may appear in example commands solely for editorial clarity; when
        present in the actual message, they are represented by "CRLF".</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IMAP Protocol Changes">
      <section anchor="suspend-command" title="SUSPEND Command">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">
            <t hangText="Arguments:">none</t>
            <t hangText="Responses:">REQUIRED untagged response: BYE<vspace/>
              OPTIONAL untagged response: SUSPEND</t>
            <t hangText="Result:">OK - logout completed<vspace/>
              BAD - command unknown or arguments invalid
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>This section defines a new SUSPEND command.</t>

        <t>To close the connection with the server, the LOGOUT command
        <xref target="RFC3501"/> is issued. The SUSPEND command extends
        the LOGOUT command by indicating to the server that, in addition
        to closing the network connection, the client also requests that
        the current configuration state be saved.</t>

        <t>If the current IMAP configuration state can be saved, an untagged
        SUSPEND response (see <xref target="suspend-response"/>) MUST be
        issued. If the server cannot save the current state, a SUSPEND
        response MUST NOT be issued.</t>

        <t>Like the LOGOUT command, a server MUST send a BYE untagged response
        before the (tagged) OK response, and then close the network
        connection.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="resume-command" title="RESUME Command">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">
            <t hangText="Arguments:">suspend token</t>
            <t hangText="Responses:">no specific response for this command</t>
            <t hangText="Result:">OK - suspend token is valid<vspace/>
              NO - suspend token is invalid<vspace/>
              BAD - command unknown or arguments invalid
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>This section defines a new RESUME command.</t>

        <t>This command is used when a client desires to restore the
        configuration state represented by a token previously generated by the
        server.</t>

        <t>The RESUME command MUST only be issued in either the not
        authenticated state or in the authenticated state. If the RESUME
        command is issued in the selected state, a BAD tagged response MUST be
        sent.</t>

        <t>If the command is sent in the not authenticated state, the client
        is indicating that it desires the restore the configuration state
        represented by the token after authentication is completed. If the
        command is issued in the authenticated state, the client is requesting
        that the current IMAP configuration be immediately switched to the
        configuration state indicated by the token.</t>

        <t>If issued in the not authenticated state, the RESUME command SHOULD
        NOT be issued until the <xref target="RFC5246">TLS</xref> layer has
        been negotiated.</t>

        <t>If the token is invalid or has expired, the RESUME command MUST
        return a tagged NO response.</t>

        <t>If the token is valid, the RESUME command MUST return a tagged OK
        response. This does NOT mean that the configuration state has been
        restored; that only occurs after the server issues a RESUME response
        code (see <xref target="resume-responsecode"/>).</t>

        <t>If the server can successfully restore the state indicated by
        the given token, it MUST issue an tagged OK response. This restored
        session MUST be identical to the state at the time the SUSPEND command
        that issued the token was issued. After a successful RESUME command,
        the connection MUST be in the authenticated state (i.e. no mailbox
        is selected).</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="suspend-response" title="SUSPEND Response">
        <t>
          <list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">
            <t hangText="Contents:">suspend token</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>The SUSPEND response occurs as a result of a SUSPEND command.
        The suspend token is a server-specific representation of the current
        configuration state of the IMAP session.</t>

        <t>[todo: A suspend token MUST become invalid if either the NAMESPACE
        or CAPABILITY configuration of the server changes.]</t>

        <t>It is RECOMMENDED that the suspend token contain a versioning
        mechanism that would cause the token to be unsuccessful in restoring
        state if the internal state storage mechanism in the server changes.
        However, interpretation of the contents or format of the suspend token
        is left entirely to the server implementor.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="resume-responsecode" title="RESUME Response Code">
        <t>This section defines a new RESUME response code:

          <list style="empty">
            <t>OK [RESUME &lt;suspend-token&gt;]</t>

            <t>where &lt;suspend-token&gt; is the token identifier associated
            with the configuration state that was restored.</t>
          </list>
        </t>

        <t>If a client issued a successful RESUME command in the not
         authenticated state, this response code MUST be issued in response to
         the authentication command.</t>

        <t>If a client issued a successful RESUME command in the authenticated
        state, this response code MUST be issued in the response to the RESUME
        command.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Implementation Considerations">
      <section title="Client">
        <t>[todo: Successfully resuming a session guarantees that the
        NAMESPACE and CAPABILITY values of the server have not changed. A
        client is RECOMMENDED to cache these values locally. Not sure if
        this is even needed, since it is a/the main reason to use this
        extension.]</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Server">
        <t>If a session is successfully resumed via a RESUME command issued
        before authentication, the client is assumed to be using a cached
        version of the CAPABILITY list. Therefore, a server SHOULD NOT
        automatically issue a CAPABILITY response code as a result of the
        authentication command since the client will already have this
        information.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>
        Example 1: A client connects to a server and does not have a saved
        suspend token. The client verifies that the server supports the
        the SUSPEND extension, performs its initialization, and obtains
        a suspend token.

        <list style="empty">
          <t>
            &lt;Client successfully authenticates to server&gt;<vspace/>
            C: A1 CAPABILITY<vspace/>
            S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 ENABLE QRESYNC I18NLEVEL=1 SUSPEND<vspace/>
            S: A1 OK Capability command completed.<vspace/>
            C: A2 ENABLE QRESYNC<vspace/>
            S: * ENABLED QRESYNC<vspace/>
            S: A2 OK Enable command completed.<vspace/>
            C: A3 LANGUAGE DE<vspace/>
            S: * LANGUAGE (DE)<vspace/>
            S: * NAMESPACE (("" "/")) (("Other Users/" "/"<vspace/>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;"TRANSLATION" ("Andere Ben&amp;APw-tzer/")))<vspace/>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(("Public Folders/" "/" "TRANSLATION"<vspace/>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;("Gemeinsame Postf&amp;AM8-cher/")))<vspace/>
            S: A3 Sprachwechsel durch LANGUAGE-Befehl ausgefuehrt<vspace/>
            [...]<vspace/>
            C: A20 SUSPEND<vspace/>
            S: * SUSPEND c3RhdGUgdG9rZW4=<vspace/>
            S: * BYE Server logging out.<vspace/>
            S: A20 OK Logout completed.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Example 2: The client in Example 1 connects at a future time to
        the same server and seeks to restore the previous IMAP session.

        <list style="empty">
          <t>
            C: * OK [CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 STARTTLS LOGINDISABLED SUSPEND]<vspace/>
            C: A1 STARTTLS<vspace/>
            S: A1 OK Being TLS negotiation now.<vspace/>
            &lt;TLS negotiation, further commands are under <xref target="RFC5246">TLS</xref> layer&gt;<vspace/>
            C: A2 CAPABILITY<vspace/>
            S: * CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 AUTH=PLAIN SUSPEND<vspace/>
            S: A2 OK CAPABILITY completed.<vspace/>
            C: A3 RESUME c3RhdGUgdG9rZW4=<vspace/>
            S: A3 OK Suspend token valid.<vspace/>
            C: A4 LOGIN joe passwd<vspace/>
            S: A4 OK [RESUME c3RhdGUgdG9rZW4=] LOGIN completed and<vspace/>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;configuration restored.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>

      <t>
        Example 3: The client in Example 1 connects at a future time to
        the same server and seeks to restore the previous IMAP session. In
        this example, the connection was pre-authenticated so the RESUME
        command is issued in the authenticated state.

        <list style="empty">
          <t>
            S: * PREAUTH [CAPABILITY IMAP4rev1 ENABLE QRESYNC I18NLEVEL=1<vspace/>
            &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;SUSPEND]<vspace/>
            C: A1 RESUME c3RhdGUgdG9rZW4=<vspace/>
            S: A1 OK [RESUME c3RhdGUgdG9rZW4=] Configuration restored.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="syntax" title="Formal Syntax">
      <t>
        The following syntax specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur
        Form (ABNF) as described in <xref target="RFC5234"/>.
        Terms not defined here are taken from <xref target="RFC3501"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        <list>
          <t>
            <list style="hanging" hangIndent="8">
              <t hangText="capability =/">"SUSPEND"</t>
              <t hangText="command-auth =/">resume / suspend</t>
              <t hangText="response-data =/">"*" SP suspend-response CRLF</t>
              <t hangText="resp-text-code =/">"RESUME" SP suspend-token</t>
              <t hangText="resume =">"RESUME" SP suspend-token</t>
              <t hangText="suspend =">"SUSPEND"</t>
              <t hangText="suspend-response =">"SUSPEND" SP suspend-token</t>
              <t hangText="suspend-token =">atom</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>The IANA is requested to add SUSPEND to the "IMAP 4 Capabilities"
      registry, http://www.iana.org/assignments/imap4-capabilities.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>It is believed that this extension doesn't add any security
      considerations that are not already present in the base IMAP
      protocol <xref target="RFC3501"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3501;
      &RFC5234;
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC2342;
      &RFC4549;
      &RFC5162;
      &RFC5246;
      &RFC5255;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
